Guide to the A. S. Brower Papers, 1939-1958 UA.29.02.0005
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
A. S. Brower papers
1939-1958
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Brower, A. S. (Alfred Smith), 1892-1968
UA.29.02.0005
9.2 Linear Feet
Brower served Duke University in the roles of Administrative Assistant, Comptroller/Business Manager and Treasurer from 1937-1962. Included in the collection are files from Brower's service to the North Carolina State Board of Education, Medical Service Association, Civil Pilot Training Program, U. S. Office of Scientific Research and Development and Duke University. The material ranges in date from 1939-1958.
approx. 5,300 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice required for use.
Provenance
The A. S. Brower Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1960, 1972-1973.
Biographical Note
Alfred Smith Brower, known as "Sol" to his friends, was born March 23, 1892 in Brower's Mills [Randolph County], North Carolina to Rufus Alfred and Mary Lee Smith Brower. He received an A.B. degree from Trinity College [Duke University] in 1912.
Before coming to Duke in 1937 as Administrative Assistant, he held several state government posts, including serving as the first director of the Division of Purchase and Contract. He was also comptroller at N. C. State University and served as Director of the Division of Finance and Statistics and the Division of Finance of Teacher Certification. Brower was appointed business manager and comptroller at Duke in 1946 and ten years later was promoted to treasurer, a post he held until his retirement in 1962.
He served as a member of the board of directors of the Medical Service Association and was president of Highland Hospital in Asheville, N.C. for more than ten years. He was also a member of the board of directors of Central Carolina Bank for more than twenty years. Additionally, Brower served as a member of the State Board of Education for twelve years. He died in 1968.
Collection Overview
The collection is divided into seven series: State Board of Education, Civil Pilot Training Program, Medical Service Association, U. S. Office of Scientific Research and Development, Duke Chapel Crypt and Oversize. The bulk of the collection pertains to the State Board of Education and the Civil Pilot Training Program and the types of materials include correspondence, reports, minutes, financial records, printed material, and photographs. Of note is the signed correspondence from architect Julian Abele in the Duke Chapel Crypt series.
Some of the paper is brittle and should be handled with care. A previous staff member attempted to remove staples from some of the material, resulting in tearing. They should also be handled with care.
Related Material
Business Division Records
Duke University Archives
Engineering, Science, and Management War Training Program Records
Duke University Archives
Office of the Treasurer Records
Duke University Archives
Undergraduate Publications Board
Duke University Archives
News Service Biographical Files
Duke University Archives
Biographical Reference Collection
Duke University Archives
Naval Reserves Officers Training Corp (NROTC) Records
Duke University Archives
Photograph Collection
Duke University Archives
Negative Collection
Duke University Archives
William Baskerville Hamilton Papers
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library at Duke University
United States. Office of Research and Development; United States. Civil Aeronautics Administration. Civil Pilot Training Program; Brower, A. S. (Alfred Smith), 1892-1968; Duke University -- Administration; Brower, A. S. (Alfred Smith), 1892-1968; Duke University. Chapel -- Crypt; North Carolina. State Board of Education -- History; Medical Service Association (Durham, N.C.)
- State Board of Education Files, 1944-1958, 2.75 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes correspondence, reports, minutes and other documents which relate to such topics as segregation and desegregation in North Carolina public schools, school construction in North Carolina, teacher salaries, the consolidation of school systems in North Carolina, and state politics. Brower served on the Board for twelve years.
  - Minutes, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Reports, Financial and Miscellaneous Documents, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Reports, Financial and Miscellaneous Documents, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Reports, Financial and Miscellaneous Documents, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Rocky Mount Commission, 1947-1948 (Box 1)
  - Reports, Financial and Miscellaneous Documents, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Reports, Financial and Miscellaneous Documents, 1948 (Box 1)
  - State School Plant Construction, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Paul Reid and C.D. Douglas, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Reports, Financial and Miscellaneous Documents, 1949 (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Librarians' Salaries, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Resolutions from Various Groups, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Rodman Loan Fund, 1949-1950 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 2)
  - Section 20 1/2 - Teacher Salaries, 1950-1951 (Box 2)
  - Resolutions from Various Groups, 1950 (Box 2)
  - Reports, Financial and Miscellaneous Documents, 1950 (Box 2)
  - Minutes, 1951 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Reports, Financial and Miscellaneous Documents, 1951 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Minutes, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1952 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Reports, Financial and Miscellaneous Documents, 1952 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 2)
  - Minutes, 1953 (Box 2)
  - Reports, Financial and Miscellaneous Documents, 1953 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Milk Commission, 1953-1955 (Box 2)
  - Minutes, 1954 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 3)
  - Reports, Financial and Miscellanous Documents, 1954 (Box 3)
  - Minutes, 1955 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1955 (Box 3)
  - Reports, Financial and Miscellanous Documents, 1955 (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Minutes, 1956 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 3)
  - Reports, Financial and Miscellaneous Documents, 1956 (Box 3)
  - State Board of Higher Education, 1956-1957 (Box 3)
  - Minutes, 1957 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 3)
  - Reports, Financial and Miscellaneous Documents, 1957 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 3)
  - Reports and Miscellaneous Documents, undated (Box 3)
  - Printed Material, 1946, 1951-1953 (Box 3)
  - Separated Material - Certificate, 1944 (Box 3)
- Civil Pilot Training Program Files, 1939-1945, 1.75 boxes
  This program was run jointly between Duke and the Civil Aeronautics Authority of the United States. Its primary objective was to train young men and women to be private pilots. By 1942, women were no longer admitted to the CPTP, however, they could enroll for the ground school program as a regular college course and could obtain flying instruction at their own expense. Though civil in nature, the program became a preparedness movement. Duke was one of the colleges and universities chosen to offer the program. Serv-Air, Inc. of Raleigh, N.C. provided the actual flight instruction. By 1942, Included in the series are samples of applications, insurance forms, time (flight) logs, course certifications, personal information sheets, and flight reports and schedules. Other files in the series have correspondence, memoranda; bulletins, annual contracts for the program, printed material and photographs. Since the classes were not part of the student's permanent record, the grades are not protected by FERPA.
  - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1940 (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1942 (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1943 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1945 (Box 4)
  - Contract for Pilot Training, 1939 (Box 4)
  - Applications - Institutional, 1939-1940, 1942, undated (Box 4)
  - Applications - Students, circa 1939-1942 (Box 4)
  - Student Rosters, 1939-1943 (Box 4)
  - Ground and Flight Instruction Contractors' Certificates, circa 1942-1943 (Box 4)
  - Flight and School Schedules; Flight Reports, 1941-1943 (Box 4)
  - Certificate of Physical Fitness, 1942 (Box 4)
  - Participants' Grades, Attendance and Evaluations, 1939-1942 (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Certificate of Ground School Completion, 1942-1943 (Box 4)
  - Students - After CPTP, 1941-1942 (Box 4)
  - Faculty (Box 4)
  - Civil Pilot Training Class Licenses (Box 4)
  - Institutional and Flight Contractor Procedure, 1942 (Box 4)
  - Reports, 1939-1940, 1942, 1943 (Box 4)
  - Regulations (Box 4)
  - Ground and Flight School Procedures, 1941 (Box 4)
  - Ground School Elementary Course, 1942-1943 (Box 4)
  - Ground School Secondary Course, 1940-1943 (Box 4)
  - Controlled Private Course, 1940-1941 (Box 4)
  - Preliminary Course, 1940 (Box 4)
  - Course: Aircraft Operation, 1941 (Box 4)
  - Course: Aerodynamics and Aircraft, undated (Box 4)
  - Course: Civil Air Regulations, 1940 (Box 4)
  - Course: Nagivation, 1940 (Box 4)
  - Course: Meteorology, 1940-1941 (Box 4)
  - Course: Aviation, 1941 (Box 4)
  - Courses: Sessions, Other, 1940-1943 (Box 4)
  - Secondary Examination (Box 4)
  - Bulletins, 1939-1940, 1942-1943 (Box 4)
  - Financial, 1940, 1942-1943 (Box 4)
  - Sample Forms (Box 5)
  - East Durham Airport, 1941 (Box 5)
  - Research on Pilot Selection Study, 1939-1940 (Box 5)
  - Photographs, circa 1939-1940, 1943 (Box 5)
  - General, Miscellaneous CPTP Documents, circa 1939-1940 (Box 5)
  - National Aviation Training Association (NATA) Newsletters, 1941 (Box 5)
  - "Civil Aeronautics Journal," 1941-1942 (Box 5)
  - Training Manuals and Pamphlets (Box 5)
  - Aviation-related Printed Materials (Box 5)
- Medical Service Association, 1940-1948, 0.5 boxes
  The Medical Service Association was a collaboration of several county medical societies in North Carolina. It was a non-profit association designed to provide a vehicle whereby members of employed groups could provide for themselves medical and surgical services on a monthly or periodic budgeting basis and allowed the individual complete freedom in choosing his/her physician. Brower served on the Board of Directors of the Association.
  - About MSA, circa 1941 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1948 (Box 6)
  - By-laws, 1940 (Box 6)
  - Agenda and Minutes from First Board Meeting, 1940 (Box 6)
  - Financial, 1940-1945 (Box 6)
  - Reports (Box 6)
  - Benefits Schedule (Box 6)
  - Certificate of Membership (Box 6)
  - Blank Forms (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
- U. S. Office of Scientific Research and Development, 1940-1946, 0.5 boxes
  This series concerns research carried out at Duke under federal government contracts during World War II. Most of the material consists of circulars and regulations, and much of it is concerned with security of research and information. There is some information on individual faculty members who worked under these contracts and their projects. There is also a contract manual dated 1945.
  - Contract Manual, 1945 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1944 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1945-1948 (Box 6)
  - Unsigned Contract (Box 6)
  - Reserved List Scientific and Technical Research Workers, circa 1943 (Box 6)
  - Outline of Facilities and Personnel Available for National Defense-related Research, 1940 (Box 6)
  - Personnel to be Awarded Certificates (Box 6)
  - OSRD Circulars, 1941-1943 (Box 6)
  - OSRD Circulars, 1944-1945 (Box 6)
  - OSRD Circular, 1946 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
- Duke Chapel Crypt, 1940-1942, 3 folders
  This series contains correspondence and architectural drawings regarding the Duke Chapel crypt. The correspondence is largely between architect Julian Abele and President William P. Few and Brower (as Administrative Assistant). The correspondence is about the placement of James A. Thomas' cremains and marker as well as the grave marker for President Few. A copy of a letter, likely written by Few to Thomas' widow, is the only known direct statement indicating that Abele was responsible for designing Duke Chapel.
  - Correspondence, 1940-1941 (Box 7)
  - Crypt Blueprints (Box 7)
  - Thomas Tablet, Bill for Thomas/Few Tablets, circa 1940-1942 (Box 7)
- Oversize
  This series contains approximately 262 Dilbert cartoons produced and published by the U. S. Navy Training Division.
  - Dilbert Cartoons (Box 7)